Preliminary Inventory of the Marek Lehnert Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Marek Lehnert papers
1984-1996
2002C12
Lehnert, Marek
10 manuscript boxes (4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Dispatches and sound recordings, relating to political conditions in Poland and to Vatican relations with Poland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
RFE/RL broadcast records, Hoover Institution Archives
RFE/RL corporate records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Radio Free Europe correspondent in Rome.
Scope and Content of Collection
Dispatches and sound recordings, relating to political conditions in Poland and to Vatican relations with Poland.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Radio Free Europe.; Catholic Church--Poland.; Radio broadcasting--Poland.; Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; Poland--Politics and government--1989-; Phonotapes.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence (Box 1)
- RFE/RL Polish service transcripts (Box 2)
- Solidarnosc file, transcripts (Box 3)
- Correspondence (Box 4)
- RFE/RL Polish service transcripts and correspondence (Box 5)
- RFE/RL Polish service transcripts and clippings (Box 6)
- Sound recordings of interviews and events, 1984-1996; 137 audio cassettes (Box 7-10)
  - Sound recording of interview with Tadeusz Kondrusiewicz, 1991 December 3 (Box 7)
    Interview with Belarusian Roman Catholic Archbishop Tadeusz Kondrusiewicz, Apostolic Administrator of European Russia, during the Synod of Bishops in Rome. Kondrusiewicz describes the position of the Catholic Church in European Russia, its challenges and successes. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005849
  - Sound recording of 4 PORY ROKU (Four Seasons) radio interview with Marek Lehnert, 1989 January 26 - 13 November 1991 (Box 7)
    Side A: 4 Pory Roku (4 Seasons) radio interview with Marek Lehnert, in Italy, about his poems published by PSIK, Polish publishing house in Italy, founded by Polish immigrants Jacek and Maria Pałasiński, Nov 13, 1991; Radio Polonia in Rome, broadcast recording.
    Side B: RADIO WOKY broadcast playing music. Selections include an instrumental rendition of the theme from M*A*S*H (Suicide Is Painless), January 26, 1989. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005850
  - Sound recording of interview with Henryk Kupiszewski and Professor Karolina Lanckorońska's award ceremony, 25-27 May 1991 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Henryk Kupiszewski, Polish Ambassador to the Vatican, discussing his planned trip to Poland to accompany John Paul II on his 4th pilgrimage, 25 May 1991.
    Side B: Lanckorońska is being awarded one of Poland's highest orders, the Polonia Restituta (Order of Rebirth of Poland), for serving the cause of freedom and promoting Polish culture, 27 May 1991. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005851
  - Sound recording of interview with Polish refugees in Rome, 1987 (Box 7)
    Polish immigrants talk about conditions in "Latina," an Italian transitional camp for refugees in Rome. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005852
  - Sound recording of interviews with Karol Modzelewski and Henryk Muszyński, 10 October - 6 December 1990 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Polish historian Karol Modzelewski, in Rome on 10 October 1990.
    Side B: Interview with Archbishop Henryk Muszyński about 25th anniversary of Nostra Aetate in Rome, on 6 December 1990. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005853
  - Sound recording of RFE broadcast "O nas samych" and interview with Marek Lehnert, 26 October 1985 - 5 April 1986 (Box 7)
    Side A: "O Nas Samych" (About Ourselves) RFE broadcast, and interview with Marek Lehnert about his work as RFE Polish correspondent in Rome, 26 October 1985.
    Side B: RFE broadcast "O Nas Samych", Marek Lehnert talks about the trial for the assassination of Pope John Paul II, 5 April 1986. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005854
  - Sound recording of RFE broadcast from Lech Wałęsa's meeting with the Polish political émigré community in Paris, 11 December 1988; Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005857 (Box 7)
  - Sound recording of interviews with Stanisław Węglarz, Lech Wałęsa, and Edmund Jan Osmańczyk, 24 May - 7 June 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Węglarz about the Independent Trade Union "Solidarity" and upcoming elections in Poland, in Rome, May 24, 1989. Also includes "Cinema & Cinema" Film interview with Lech Wałęsa in Rome.
    Side B: Interview with Polish journalist Edmund Osmańczyk about the 1989 legislative election in Poland, June 7, 1989, in Rome. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005858
  - Sound recording of interviews with Józef Ślisz and Beniamino (Nino) Andreatta, 25 - 27 September 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Ślisz, Chairman of Solidarity of Independent Farmers, during his visit to the Vatican, 25 September 1989.
    Side B: Interview with Andreatta, 27 September 1989. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005862
  - Sound recording of Pope John Paul II's visit to Lithuania, September 1993 (Box 7)
    Side A: Pope John Paul II in Vilnius, Lithuania, mass for Poles, on September 7, 1993.
    Side B: Interview with Archbishop Tadeusz Kondrusiewicz in September 1993. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005863
  - Sound recording "Odjazd Władka" (Władek's departure), 2 August 1987 (Box 7)
    Interview with Polish immigrants before their departure from a transitional camp for refugees in Italy, about their reasons for leaving Poland and expectations regarding their final destinations: Canada, Australia, and USA. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005865
  - Sound recording of U3 Uchodźcy interviews of Polish refugees, 1988 (Box 7)
    Polish refugees in Italy talk about the interviews they had in Canadian, American, or Australian embassies in Rome, before being granted permission to legally emigrate to those countries. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005867
  - Sound recording of Radio Vatican broadcast featuring Tadeusz Mazowiecki's meeting with Pope John Paul II, 20 October 1989 (Box 7)
    This Radio Vatican Polish section broadcast includes an announcement about Tadeusz Mazowiecki, Chairman of the Council of Ministers in Poland, who visited St. Peter's Basilica in Rome to meet with Pope John Paul II. In Polish. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005868
  - Sound recording of Lech Wałęsa's visit to the Vatican, 5 February 1991 (Box 7)
    Welcoming speech to Wałęsa, president of Poland, who visited the Vatican and met with Pope John Paul II. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005870
  - Sound recording of the Central European Initiative summit in Italy, 1988 - 3 February 1993 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interviews with ministers of Poland and other European countries during the Central European Initiative summit in Italy.
    Side B: Radio Vatican announcement about Pope John Paul II's trip to the African countries Benin, Uganda, and Sudan, February 3, 1993. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005871
  - Sound recording of interviews with Jerzy Hordyński and Bishop Stanisław Stefanek, 16 July - 28 November 1992 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Polish poet and writer Hordyński, July 16, 1992.
    Side B: Interview with Stefanek about the assembly of bishops dedicated to Christian families, on 28 November, 1992. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005874
  - Sound recording of the Primate's Social Council press conference and interviews with Bronisław Geremek and Adam Michnik, 27 February - 14 August 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Press conference with the Primate's Social Council members visiting Rome: actor Andrzej Łapicki, Mochlińska, and others, February 27 1989.
    Side B: Interview with Geremek and Michnik at the airport before leaving Rome about their visit in Italy and the political transformation in Poland, August 14 1989. Radio Vatican sound recording. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005875
  - Sound recording of Radio Vatican Polish news broadcast: interview with Polish refugees before their departure to Australia, 1988 (Box 7)
    Side A: Radio Vatican Polish section news broadcast, including commentary about Pope John Paul II's visit to Bolivia, Peru, and Paraguay, also other news from Poland, 1988.
    Side B: Interview with Polish refugees conducted at the airport before their departure to Australia, "Kubuś Jedzie do Australii." The family talks about their fifteen-month experience as refugees living in Italian transitional camp and expectations about their final destination of Australia. A young boy named Kubuś is excited about flying to Australia. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005879
  - Sound recording of interview with Lech Wałęsa in Florence, 22 October 1995 (Box 7)
    Interview with Polish president Wałęsa during his visit to Florence. He talks about his presidency and political and economic challenges awaiting Polish new post-communist democracy. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005880
  - Sound recording of "Cinema & Cinema" radio broadcast featuring an interview with Lech Wałęsa, 8 May 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Wałęsa on the "Cinema & Cinema" Italian radio station, with an Italian interpreter.
    Side B: Radio Vatican broadcast. In Polish. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005992
  - Sound recording of Radio Vatican Polish broadcast, 23 April 1988 (Box 7)
    Side A: Radio Vatican Polish broadcast: Archbishop Miroslav Marusyn, Secretary of the Congregation for the Eastern Churches. Also excerpts from liturgy of the Eucharist for Saint Adalbert (Ŝw.Wojciech) by Pope John Paul II, April 23 1988.
    Side B: Radio Vatican Polish broadcast, 1988, including information on Catholic Church hierarchy in Poland and other news related to Pope John Paul II and Catholic Church. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005993
  - Sound recording of "Podarunek od VI klasy" and interview with Lech Wałęsa, 15 January 1986 (Box 7)
    Side A: "Podarunek od VI klasy" (a gift from the sixth graders): interview with Polish 6th grader about a religious cross in his classroom in Poland, which he gave to Soviet delegation as a gift. the boy was later interrogated by the Polish Secret Service.
    Side B: Interview with Wałęsa, January 15 1986. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005994
  - Zbigniew Bujak sound recording, 27-28 October 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Zbigniew Bujak, "Solidarity" leader, at the Symposium on Prestroika in Rome, October 27 1989. Bujak talks about the "Solidarity" Trade Union and reforms in Poland.
    Side B: Interview with Zbigniew Bujak, October 28 1989. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0005995
  - Sound recording of interviews with Lech Wałęsa and Władysław Bartoszewski, 22 October - 3 November 1995 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Polish President Wałęsa in Florence about upcoming parliamentary elections in Poland, October 22 1995; Cardinal Etchegaray.
    Side B: Interview with Bartoszewski, Minister of Foreign Affairs in Poland, in Rome, 2-3 November 1995. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006003
  - Obóz "Latina" sound recording, 28-29 July 1987 (Box 7)
    Side A: Obóz "Latina" ("Latina" camp), July 28, 1987. This is Lehnert's detailed report of his visit to camp "Latina," a transitional camp in Rome that is the temporary home for refugees of various countries, mostly from Poland, before they get permission to immigrate to countries of their final destination. Lehnert describes the camp's buildings and living conditions, he also interviews one Polish resident.
    Side B: Polish mass in the camp's chapel, more interviews with Polish residents. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006004
  - Sound recording of interview of Lech Wałęsa visiting Rome, April 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Wałęsa and his speech during his visit to Rome, April 1989, where he met with Italian politicians and members of the democratic party: Benvenuto, Craxi, and Occhetto.
    Side B: Speech by Piotr Nowina-Konopka, an assistant and spokesman for Wałęsa and Solidarity spokesman at the 1989 Round Table Agreement negotiations, on April 21 1989 in Rome. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006006
  - Sound recording of interview with Władysław Frasyniuk and Janusz Pałubicki, 14 July 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Frasyniuk and Pałubicki, Polish politicians, activists of Solidarity trade union, during their visit in Rome
    Side B: Radio Vatican Polish Section broadcast. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006007
  - Sound recording of interviews with Krzysztof Zanussi and Jerzy Hordyński, 2-3 October 1990 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Zanussi, Polish film director and producer, during his visit in Rome, October 2 1990, about cinematography and TV production in Poland during transformation period. Zanussi also recalls recently deceased Italian novelist and journalist Alberto Moravia.
    Side B: Interview with Polish poet and writer Hordyński, who talks about recently deceased popular Italian novelist and journalist Alberto Moravia, from October 3 1990; Pope John Paul II on abortion. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006010
  - Sound recording of Adam Michnik and Konstanty Gebert (Dawid Warszawski), 28-29 October 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Michnik, prominent "Solidarity" activist and dissident, speaks during a panel discussion about political and democratic transformation in Poland and other Eastern European countries, October 28 1989.
    Side B: Interview with Gebert (pseudonym Dawid Warszawski), Polish journalist and Jewish activist, October 29 1989. Gebert talks about the new government in Poland, established after Round Table negotiations and democratic elections, and emerging challenges and problems in new political landscape. He emphasizes the new role and responsibilities of the press in Poland. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006011
  - Uchodźcy (refugees) sound recording (Part 4), 1988 (Box 7)
    Interview with Polish refugees about possibilities and conditions of returning to their homeland, in light of recent political events there, recognition of Solidarity and economic and social circumstances in Poland. All interviewees do not believe in true reforms and are convinced that they made the right decision by leaving Poland. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006012
  - Sound recording of interviews with Jacek Woźniakowski and Stefan Frankiewicz, 5 November 1991 (Box 7)
    Side A: Interview with Professor Woźniakowski, Polish art historian, writer, journalist, member of the Citizens' Committee of Solidarity and first elected president of Krakow after the collapse of communism. As correspondent of the Catholic newspaper "Universal Weekly," Woźniakowski talks about the symposium at the Vatican in which he gave a speech about changes in post-communist Poland, especially the role of Church.
    Side B: Interview with Professor Frankiewicz, Polish historian, journalist, ambassador to Vatican, and Chief Editor of Catholic monthly "Więź"(Bond). Frankiewicz talks about the symposium where he spoke on religion and culture in uniting post-communist Europe. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006013
  - Sound recording of interviews with Piero Schiavazzi and Piotr Konopka, 17 April 1989 (Box 7)
    Side A: Italian journalist Schiavazzi talks about "Persona TV" (recording in Italian).
    Side B: Nowina-Konopka, Polish politician, assistant and spokesman for Lech Wałęsa, leader of the Solidarity movement, talks about his work with Wałęsa and the Round Table Negotiations. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006016
  - Sound recording of interviews with Interview with Archbishop Henryk Muszyński and Lech Wałęsa, 1 July 1994 (Box 7)
    Side A: Archbishop Muszyński talks about council preparatory sessions for an upcoming 1994 Synod in Rome. Interview conducted on July 1 1994.
    Side B: Wałęsa talks on an Italian radio program, 1994 (questions in Italian); Pope John Paul II greets pilgrims from different countries in Rome. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006017
  - Sound recording of interview with Andrzej Stelmachowski and Maja Komorowska, 15 March - 17 May 1990 (Box 7)
    Side A: Andrzej Stelmachowski, Marshal of the Senate, talks about pilgrimages of John Paul II to Poland, elections and political scene in Poland, also role of Polish diaspora in Western countries, 15 March 1990.
    Side B: Interview with Polish actress and teacher Maja Komorowska about the theater festival in Rome and challenges for new actors in politically transforming Poland, 17 May 1990. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006018
  - TG1 Speciale 3 radio station sound recording, 15 January 1987 (Box 8)
    Label reads: TG1 SPECIALE (3) 15.I.87. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006021
  - Sound recording of an interview with Jerzy Urban and a reading of the novel "Potop" (part I), 9 December 1988 (Box 8)
    Side A: Urban, journalist, reporter, and a Polish government spokesperson from 1981 to 1989, talks about positive political and economic changes in Poland, also the ruling communist party's dialogue with the "Solidarity" movement and opposition. The interview was conducted during Urban's visit to Rome, December 9, 1988.
    Side B: "Potop," a patriotic historical novel by Polish writer Henryk Sienkiewicz, part I. The novel is read by actors from radio program. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006023
  - Sound recording Praca (work) of interviews with Polish immigrants, undated (Box 8)
    This interview with Polish immigrants is about finding work while staying in a transitional camp in Rome, Italy. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006026
  - Sound recording of Slovak politician Alexander Dubček accepting an honorary doctorate from Bologna University in Italy, 13-14 November 1988; Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006027 (Box 8)
  - Sound recording of interviews with Tadeusz Kantor and Alicja Grześkowiak, 11-13 June 1990 (Box 8)
    Side A: Tadeusz Kantor, Polish artist, painter, set designer and theater director, talks about his attitude toward culture and art in politically transformed Poland, during his visit to Rome in June 1990. Kantor describes new challenges facing artists in Poland, especially in the "theatrical world."
    Side B: Interview with Grześkowiak, member of Polish Senate, during her diplomatic visit to Rome in 1990 June. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006028
  - Sound recording of interview with Henryk Kupiszewski, 11-16 June 1990 (Box 8)
    Side A: Professor Kupiszewski, Polish ambassador to the Vatican, talks about changes and new perspectives on a global scale after reinstating diplomatic relations between Poland and the Vatican. He points out the important role of Pope John Paul II's recent visit to Poland.
    Side B: Italian actor Alberto Sordi, 1990. In Italian. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006029
  - Sound recording of Professor Włodzimierz Mokry and Marek Król, 28 October 1989 (Box 8)
    Side A: Mokry, a Polish professor of Ukrainian origin and member of Parliament, talks about Ukraine and other former Soviet republics' national identities and the future of the Russian Federation.
    Side B: Interview with Król, Polish journalist, activist of the Communist Party, former editor of "Wprost,"and member of Parliament. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006111
  - Sound recording of Marek Lehnert speaking about the Pontificia Academia Ecclesiastica (Pontifical Academy of Church) in Rome, 19 April 1987 (Box 8)
    Founded in 1706, this elite Church Academy specializes in Vatican Diplomacy. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006112
  - Sound recording of a Radio Vatican broadcast concerning Pope John Paul II's stay in the Gemelli Polyclinic, July 1992 (Box 8)
    Report concerns the Pope's health. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006113
  - Sound recording of Josip Terelja and other Catholic Church leaders at a press conference, 5 February 1988 (Box 8)
    Side A: Terelja, Lay Leader of Ukrainian Catholics, at a press conference in Rome. Terelja spent many years in Soviet prisons and psychiatric hospitals because of his campaign for recognition of the rights of Ukrainian Catholics. Italian radio broadcast.
    Side B: Press conference with leaders of Ukrainian Catholic Church at the Vatican. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006114
  - Sound recording of interviews of Professor Bronisław Geremek and Cardinal Henryk Gulbinowicz, 18-29 January 1991 (Box 8)
    Side A: Interview with Polish historian and politician Geremek, during his visit to Rome, 18 January 1991. Geremek talks about Polish reaction to the recent outbreak of war in the Middle East, also Polish-Russian political and economic relations.
    Side B: Interview with Gulbinowicz about the role of the Catholic Church in post-communist Poland, 29 January 1991. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006116
  - Sound recording of interview with Władysław Frasyniuk and Janusz Pałubicki, 14 July 1989 (Box 8)
    Interview with Frasyniuk, politician, former activist of Solidarity Trade Union, member of Polish parliament, and Pałubicki, Polish politician and activist, during their visit to Rome, 14 July 1989. They discuss the need for economic reforms in a free-market-economy Poland, ways of improving the standard of living, and decreasing the identity and role of "Solidarity" Free Union. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006117
  - Sound recording of interview with Professor Jacek Woźniakowski and Piotr Nowina-Konopka, 16-18 January 1990 (Box 8)
    Side A: Professor Woźniakowski, Polish art historian, novelist, journalist, member of the Citizens' Committee to the President of Trade Union "Solidarity," comments on Polish reaction to Pope John Paul II's recent address, and political and economic reforms in Poland.
    Side B: Nowina-Konopna, spokesman for Solidarity leader Lech Wałęsa and Solidarity spokesman at the 1989 Round Table Agreement negotiations, talks about the political scene in Poland. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006118
  - Sound recording of interview of Father Ivan Dacko, 25 July 1991 (Box 8)
    Dacko, aUkrainian Greek Catholic priest, served as patriarchal chancellor of the Ukrainian Catholic Church based in Rome. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006119
  - Sound recording of interviews with Konrad Hejmo and Grzegorz Gałązka, 2-3 September 1992 (Box 8)
    Side A: Interview with Hejmo, Polish Catholic priest, assistant to the general and special audiences of Pope John Paul II. Hejmo talks about the challenges of arranging audiences for Polish pilgrims after the Pope's illness and surgery in July 1992.
    Side B: Gałązka, official photographer of Pope John Paul II, comments on the Pope's recent trip to the mountains after his illness and hospitalization. Gałązka accompanied Pope during his trip. Use copy reference number: 2002c12_a_0006121